
Tutorials Point *************************************************************************************

=========================================================================================================================
Basics of CouchDB
=========================================================================================================================

CouchDB is an open source database developed by Apache software foundation. The focus is on the ease of use, embracing the web. It is a NoSQL document store database.

It uses JSON, to store data (documents), java script as its query language to transform the documents, http protocol for api to access the documents, 
query the indices with the web browser. It is a multi master application released in 2005 and it became an apache project in 2008.

CouchDB was written in Erlang programming language.

You can interact with the CouchDB web interface by using the following url −

http://127.0.0.1:5984/_utils/


========================================================================================================================
CouchDB with cURL and Futon
========================================================================================================================

===================
cURL
===================

cURL utility is a way to communicate with CouchDB.

It is a tool to transfer data from or to a server, using one of the supported protocols (HTTP, HTTPS, FTP, FTPS, TFTP, DICT, TELNET, LDAP or FILE). 
This command is designed to work without user interaction. cURL offers a busload of useful tricks like proxy support, user authentication, ftp upload, HTTP post,
 SSL (https:) connections, cookies, file transfer resume and more.

The cURL utility is available for operating systems such as UNIX, Linux, Mac OS X and Windows. It is a command-line utility to access HTTP protocol 
straight away from the command line.

Using cURL Utility
You can access any website using cURL utility by simply typing cURL followed by the website address as shown below −

curl www.tutorialspoint.com/
By default, the cURL utility returns the source code of the requested page. It displays this code on the terminal window.

cURL Utility Options
cURL utility provides various options to work with, and you can see them in cURL utility help.

The following code shows some portion of cURL help.

$ curl --help
While communicating with CouchDB, certain options of cURL utility were extensively used. Following are the brief descriptions of some important options of cURL utility including those used by CouchDB −

-X flag
When communicating with an HTTP server, -X flag allows to specify a request method (GET, POST, PUT etc.) to override the default method(GET).
When communicating with an FTP server, -X flag allows to specify FTP command to override the default command(LIST).

-H
This flag specifies a custom header to pass on to the server. For example, to send a file to the server, we have to use the "content type" that defines the type of content of the file that we are going to upload.

-d flag
Using this flag of cURL, you can send data along with the HTTP POST request to the server, as if it was filled by the user in the form and submitted.

Example :

Suppose there is a website and you want to login into it or send some data to the website using –d flag of cURL utility as shown below.

curl -X PUT http://mywebsite.com/login.html -d userid=001 -d password=tutorialspoint
It sends a post chunk that looks like "userid=001&password=tutorialspoint". Likewise you can also send documents (JSON ) using -d flag.

-o flag
Using this flag, cURL writes the output of the request to a file.

Example :

The following example shows the use of -o flag of cURL utility.

$ curl -o example.html www.tutorialspoint.com/index.htm 
% Total % Received % Xferd Average Speed Time Time Time Current 
      Dload Upload Total Spent Left Speed
100 81193 0 81193 0 0 48168 0 --:--:-- 0:00:01 --:--:--
58077
This gets the source code of the homepage of tutorialspoint.com, creates a file named example.com and saves the output in the file named example.html.


-O
This flag is similar to –o, the only difference is with this flag, a new file with the same name as the requested url was created, and the source code of the requested url will be copied to it.

Example :

The following example shows the use of -O flag of cURL utility.

$ curl -O www.tutorialspoint.com/index.htm
% Total % Received % Xferd Average Speed Time Time Time Current
      Dload Upload Total Spent Left
Speed
100 81285 0 81285 0 0 49794 0 --:--:-- 0:00:01 --:--:--
60077
It creates a new file with the name index.htm and saves the source code of the index page of tutorialspoint.com in it.


// Hello CouchDB
You can access the homepage of the CouchDB by sending a GET request to the CouchDB instance installed. First of all make sure you have installed CouchDB in your Linux environment and it is running successfully, and then use the following syntax to send a get request to the CouchDB instance.

curl http://127.0.0.1:5984/
This gives you a JSON document as shown below where CouchDB specifies the details such as version number, name of the vendor, and version of the software.

$ curl http://127.0.0.1:5984/
{
   "couchdb" : "Welcome",
   "uuid" : "8f0d59acd0e179f5e9f0075fa1f5e804",
   "version" : "1.6.1",
   "vendor" : {
      "name":"The Apache Software Foundation",
      "version":"1.6.1"
   }
}




// List of All Databases
You can get the list of all the databases created, by sending a get request along with the string "_all_dbs string ". Following is the syntax to get the list of all databases in CouchDB.

curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/_all_dbs
It gives you the list of all databases in CouchDB as shown below.

$ curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/_all_dbs
[ "_replicator" , "_users" ]


// Creating a Database
You can create a database in CouchDB using cURL with PUT header using the following syntax −

$ curl -X PUT http://127.0.0.1:5984/database_name
Example
As an example, using the above given syntax create a database with name my_database as shown below.

$ curl -X PUT http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database
{"ok":true}


// Verification
Verify whether the database is created, by listing out all the databases as shown below. Here you can observe the name of newly created database, "my_database" in the list

$ curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/_all_dbs

[ "_replicator " , "_users" , "my_database" ]



// Getting Database Info
You can get the information about database using the get request along with the database name. Following is the syntax to get the database information.

Example
As an example let us get the information of the database named my_database as shown below. Here you can get the information about your database as a response.

$ curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database

{
   "db_name" : "my_database",
   "doc_count" : 0,
   "doc_del_count" : 0,
   "update_seq" : 0,
   "purge_seq" : 0,
   "compact_running" : false,
   "disk_size" : 79,
   "data_size" : 0,
   "instance_start_time" : "1423628520835029",
   "disk_format_version" : 6,
   "committed_update_seq" : 0
 }



================================
Futon
================================

Futon
Futon is the built-in, web based, administration interface of CouchDB. It provides a simple graphical interface using which you can interact with CouchDB. 
It is a naive interface and it provides full access to all CouchDB features. Following is the list of those features −

Databases −
Creates databases.
Destroys databases.
Documents −
Creates documents.
Updates documents.
Edits documents.
Deletes documents.


// Starting Futon
Make sure CouchDB is running and then open the following url in browser −

http://127.0.0.1:5984/_utils/


===================================
HTTP API
===================================

Using HTTP request headers, you can communicate with CouchDB. Through these requests we can retrieve data from the database, store data in to the database 
in the form of documents, and we can view as well as format the documents stored in a database.


// HTTP Request Formats
While communicating with the database we will use different request formats like get, head, post, put, delete, and copy. For all operations in CouchDB, the input data and the output data structures will be in the form of JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) object.

Following are the different request formats of HTTP Protocol used to communicate with CouchDB.

GET − This format is used to get a specific item. To get different items, you have to send specific url patterns. In CouchDB using this GET request, we can get static items, database documents and configuration, and statistical information in the form of JSON documents (in most cases).

HEAD − The HEAD method is used to get the HTTP header of a GET request without the body of the response.

POST − Post request is used to upload data. In CouchDB using POST request, you can set values, upload documents, set document values, and can also start certain administration commands.

PUT − Using PUT request, you can create new objects, databases, documents, views and design documents.

DELETE − Using DELETE request, you can delete documents, views, and design documents.

COPY − Using COPY method, you can copy documents and objects.



// HTTP Request Headers
HTTP headers should be supplied to get the right format and encoding. While sending the request to the CouchDB server, you can send Http request headers along with the request. Following are the different Http request headers.

Content-type − This Header is used to specify the content type of the data that we supply to the server along with the request. Mostly the type of the content we send along with the request will be MIME type or JSON (application/json). Using Content-type on a request is highly recommended.

Accept − This header is used to specify the server, the list of data types that client can understand, so that the server will send its response using those data types. Generally here, you can send the list of MIME data types the client accepts, separated by colons.

Though, using Accept in queries of CouchDB is not required, it is highly recommended to ensure that the data returned can be processed by the client.


// Response Headers
These are the headers of the response sent by the server. These headers give information about the content send by the server as response.

Content-type − This header specifies the MIME type of the data returned by the server. For most request, the returned MIME type is text/plain.

Cache-control − This header suggests the client about treating the information sent by the server. CouchDB mostly returns the must-revalidate, which indicates that the information should be revalidated if possible.

Content-length − This header returns the length of the content sent by the server, in bytes.

Etag − This header is used to show the revision for a document, or a view.


// Status Codes
Following is the tabular form of the status code sent by the http header and the description of it.

200 − OK	This status will be issued when a request completed successfully.
201 − Created	This status will be issued when a document is created.
202 − Accepted	This status will be issued when a request is accepted.
404 − Not Found	This status will be issued when the server is unable to find the requested content.
405 − Resource Not Allowed	This status is issued when the HTTP request type used is invalid.
409 − Conflict	This status is issued whenever there is any update conflict.
415 − Bad Content Type	This status indicated that the requested content type is not supported by the server.
500 − Internal Server Error	This status is issued whenever the data sent in the request is invalid.


// HTTP URL Paths
There are certain url paths using which, you can interact with the database directly. Following is the tabular format of such url paths.

URL	Operation
PUT /db	This url is used to create a new database.
GET /db	This url is used to get the information about the existing database.
PUT /db/document	This url is used to create a document/update an existing document.
GET /db/document	This url is used to get the document.
DELETE /db/document	This url is used to delete the specified document from the specified database.
GET /db/_design/design-doc	This url is used to get the definition of a design document.
GET /db/_design/designdoc/_view/view-name	This url is used to access the view, view-name from the design document from the specified database.


=========================
Creating Database
=========================

// Creating a Database using cURL Utility
You can create a database in CouchDB by sending an HTTP request to the server using PUT method through cURL utility. Following is the syntax to create a database −

$ curl -X PUT http://127.0.0.1:5984/database_name
Using −X we can specify HTTP custom request method to be used. In this case, we are using PUT method. When we use the PUT operation/method, the content of the url specifies the object name we are creating using HTTP request. Here we have to send the name of the database using put request in the url to create a database.

Example
Using the above given syntax if you want to create a database with name my_database, you can create it as mentioned below. As a response the server will return you a JSON document with content "ok" : true indicating the operation was successful.

curl -X PUT http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database
{
   "ok":true
}
Verification
Verify whether the database is created, by listing out all the databases as shown below. Here you can observe the name of a newly created database, " my_database " in the list.

$ curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/_all_dbs

[ "_replicator " , " _users " , " my_database " ]


// Creating a Database using Futon
To create a database open the http://127.0.0.1:5984/_utils/.


===============================
Deleting a database
===============================

//  Deleting a Database using cURL Utility
You can delete a database in CouchDB by sending a request to the server using DELETE method through cURL utility. Following is the syntax to create a database −

$ curl -X DELETE http://127.0.0.1:5984/database_name
Using −X we can specify a custom request method of HTTP we are using, while communicating with the HTTP server. In this case, we are using the DELETE method. Send the url to the server by specifying the database to be deleted in it.

Example
Assume there is a database named my_database2 in CouchDB. Execute the command as mentioned below. Server should respond you with a JSON document having "ok" : true indicating the operation was successful.

$ curl -X DELETE http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database2
{
   "ok" : true
}
Verification
Verify whether the database is deleted by listing out all the databases as shown below. Here you can observe the name of the deleted database, "my_database" is not there in the list.

$ curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/_all_dbs

[ "_replicator " , " _users " ]

// Deleting a Database using Futon
To delete a database, open the http://127.0.0.1:5984/_utils/


==============================================
Creating Document
==============================================

//  Creating a Document using cURL Utility
You can create a document in CouchDB by sending an HTTP request to the server using PUT method through cURL utility. Following is the syntax to create a document.

$ curl -X PUT http://127.0.0.1:5984/database name/"id" -d ' { document} '
Using −X, we can specify a custom request method of HTTP we are using, while communicating with the HTTP server. In this case, we are using PUT method. When we use the PUT method, the content of the url specifies the object name we are creating using the HTTP request. Here we have to send the following −

The name of the database name in which we are creating the document.

The document id.

The data of the document. −d option is used to send the data/document through HTTP request. While writing a document simply enter your Field-Value pairs separated by colon, within flower brackets as shown below −

{
   Name : Raju
   age : 23
   Designation : Designer
}
Example
Using the above given syntax if you want to create a document with id 001 in a database with name my_database, you can create it as shown below.

$ curl -X PUT http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database/"001" -d
'{ " Name " : " Raju " , " age " :" 23 " , " Designation " : " Designer " }'

{"ok":true,"id":"001","rev":"1-1c2fae390fa5475d9b809301bbf3f25e"}
The response of CouchDB to this request contains three fields −

"ok", indicating the operation was successful.

"id", which stores the id of the document and

"rev", this indicates the revision id. Every time you revise (update or modify) a document a _rev value will be generated by CouchDB. If you want to update or delete a document, CouchDB expects you to include the _rev field of the revision you wish to change. When CouchDB accepts the change, it will generate a new revision number. This mechanism ensures concurrency control.

Verification
If you want to view the created document you can get it using the document as shown below.

$ curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database/001
{
   "_id": "001",
   "_rev": "1-3fcc78daac7a90803f0a5e383f4f1e1e",
   "Name": "Raju",
   "age": 23,
   "Designation": "Designer"
}


//  Creating a Document using Futon
To Create a document open the http://127.0.0.1:5984/_utils/ url to get an Overview/index page of CouchDB as shown below.


======================================
Deleting a document
======================================

// Deleting a Document using cURL Utility
You can delete a document in CouchDB by sending an HTTP request to the server using DELETE method through cURL utility. Following is the syntax to delete a document.

curl -X DELETE http://127.0.0.1:5984/database_name/database_id?_rev
Using −X, we can specify a custom request method of HTTP we are using, while communicating with the HTTP server. In this case, we are using Delete method. To delete a database /database_name/database_id/ is not enough. You have to pass the recent revision id through the url. To mention attributes of any data structure "?" is used.

Example
Suppose there is a document in database named my_database with document id 001. To delete this document, you have to get the rev id of the document. Get the document data as shown below.

$ curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database/001
{
   " _id " : " 001 ",
   " _rev " : " 2-04d8eac1680d237ca25b68b36b8899d3 " ,
   " age " : " 23 "
}
Now specify the revision id of the document to be deleted, id of the document, and database name the document belongs to, as shown below −

$ curl -X DELETE http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database/001?rev=1-
3fcc78daac7a90803f0a5e383f4f1e1e

{"ok":true,"id":"001","rev":"2-3a561d56de1ce3305d693bd15630bf96"}
Verification
To verify whether the document is deleted, try to fetch the document by using the GET method. Since you are fetching a deleted document, this will give you an error message as shown below −

$ curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database/001
{"error":"not_found","reason":"deleted"}

// Deleting a Document using Futon
using the https url as decribed above.


=======================================
Updating documents
=======================================

// Updating Documents using cURL
You can update a document in CouchDB by sending an HTTP request to the server using PUT method through cURL utility. Following is the syntax to update a document.

curl -X PUT http://127.0.0.1:5984/database_name/document_id/ -d '{ "field" : "value", "_rev" : "revision id" }'
Example
Suppose there is a document with id 001 in the database named my_database.

First of all, get the revision id of the document that is to be updated. You can find the _rev of the document in the document itself, as shown below −

$ curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database/001
{
   "_id" : "001",
   "_rev" : "2-04d8eac1680d237ca25b68b36b8899d3 " ,
   "age" : "23"
}
Use revision id _rev from the document. In this example, we are updating the age from 23 to 24.

$ curl -X PUT http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database/001/ -d
' { " age " : " 24 " , " _rev " : " 1-1c2fae390fa5475d9b809301bbf3f25e " } '

{ " ok " : true , " id " : " 001 " , " rev " : " 2-04d8eac1680d237ca25b68b36b8899d3 " }
Verification
To verify the document, get the document again using GET request as shown below −

$ curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database/001
{
   " _id " : " 001 ",
   " _rev " : " 2-04d8eac1680d237ca25b68b36b8899d3 " ,
   " age " : " 23 "
 }
Note −
Following are some important points to be noted while updating a document.

The URL we send in the request containing the database name and the document id.

Updating an existing document is same as updating the entire document. You cannot add a field to an existing document. You can only write an entirely new version of the document into the database with the same document ID.

We have to supply the revision number as a part of the JSON request.

In return JSON contains the success message, the ID of the document being updated, and the new revision information. If you want to update the new version of the document, you have to quote this latest revision number.

// Updating Documents using Futon
To delete a document open the http://127.0.0.1:5984/_utils/




==================================
Attaching files
==================================

// Attaching Files using cURL
You can attach files to CouchDB just like email. The file contains metadata like name and includes its MIME type, and the number of bytes the attachment contains. To attach files to a document you have to send PUT request to the server. Following is the syntax to attach files to the document −

$ curl -vX PUT http://127.0.0.1:5984/database_name/database_id
/filename?rev=document rev_id --data-binary @filename -H "Content-Type:
type of the content"
The request has various options that are explained below.

--data-binary@ - This option tells cURL to read a file’s contents into the HTTP request body.

-H - This option is used to mention the content type of the file we are going to upload.

Example
Let us attach a file named boy.jpg, to the document with id 001, in the database named my_database by sending PUT request to CouchDB. Before that, you have to fetch the data of the document with id 001 to get its current rev id as shown below.

$ curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database/001
{
   "_id": "001",
   "_rev": "1-967a00dff5e02add41819138abb3284d"
}
Now using the _rev value, send the PUT request to the CouchDB server as shown below.

$ curl -vX PUT http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database/001/boy.jpg?rev=1-
967a00dff5e02add41819138abb3284d --data-binary @boy.jpg -H "ContentType:
image/jpg"
Verification
To verify whether the attachment is uploaded, fetch the document content as shown below−

$ curl -X GET http://127.0.0.1:5984/my_database/001
{
   "_id": "001",
   "_rev": "2-4705a219cdcca7c72aac4f623f5c46a8",
   "_attachments": {
      "boy.jpg": {
         "content_type": "image/jpg",
         "revpos": 2,
         "digest": "md5-9Swz8jvmga5mfBIsmCxCtQ==",
         "length": 91408,
         "stub": true
      }
   }
}


// Attaching Files using Futon
Upload Attachment
Using this option, you can upload a new attachment such as a file, image, or document, to the database.
 To do so, click on the Upload Attachment button. A dialog box will appear where you can choose the file to be uploaded. Select the file and click on the Upload button.

